Okay, so we're on our new מסכת שקלים, Masechet Shekalim, which we
have ירושלמי Yerushalmi on. Everybody wants to know why is שקלים Shekalim
included in the דף יומי. Daf Yomi. I don't have, I only
have my speculations, although somebody told me they thought they saw some,
somebody did a study on it. I mean, it's really the decision
of the first דף יומי Daf Yomi to include it. My guess
is that, first of all, it's printed in the בבלי, Bavli, and
I don't know of any other ירושלמי Yerushalmi that we have that's
printed in the בבלי. Bavli. Of course, that begs the question: why
is it printed in the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi? I mean, maybe the answer
to both of them is the same, which is that it's the
one מסכת Masechet in מועד Moed that we don't have covered in
the בבלי. Bavli. So opposed to זרעים, Zeraim, where we only have
ברכות, Brachot, this is the one exclusion and it's small, so maybe
it was done for completion. But be that as it may, we
are doing שקלים Shekalim with ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
שקלים Shekalim also in terms of the organization of the מסכת Masechet
of the סדר Seder comes after יומא. Yoma. People might be aware,
since the normal order of the מסכתות Masechtot in a סדר Seder
go by the number of פרקים. Perakim. So conveniently, you have שבת
Shabbat and עירובין, Eruvin, which are conceptually first anyway, and then you
have פסחים, Pesachim, and if you say, you know, החודש הזה לכם,
HaChodesh Hazeh Lachem, it starts with ניסן, Nissan, so that all works
out very nicely. But then the next one after that is יומא,
Yoma, יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, which does not work so well. So
we actually have reorganized that for the בבלי Bavli and made it
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, יומא, Yoma, סוכה, Sukkah, so that's in the
order of the מועדים Moadim that come in תשרי. Tishrei. There's nothing
on שבועות, Shavuot, so it works perfectly. You have the ניסן Nissan
מועד Moed and then you have the תשרי Tishrei מועדים, Moadim, it
looks perfectly. But it really is not that way. It's really that
יומא Yoma comes first, and it's really that שקלים Shekalim comes after
יומא Yoma because שקלים Shekalim has fewer פרקים Perakim than יומא. Yoma.
But I imagine the reason it was put here is because, as
we saw, you're collecting right around פסח Pesach time, you start באחד
באדר, Be-Echad Be-Adar, and you're bringing the, you want the new שקלים
Shekalim gathered for ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. So it is,
you know, so it, I don't know, but it's actually it's more
in that פרשה, Parsha, so hence the organization of it here.
There's also some social cultural tension maybe, the ancients did things as
you said simply pragmatically by how long they were.
Right. But we want things to have a little bit more, the
first word.
Right. The Quran is actually organized that way.
Oh god. Anyway, no, just said that because I tried reading that
and it's not easy reading. Anyway,
so let's take up now on what's ג עמוד א, Gimel Amud
Aleph, but that's always never really the way to refer to the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi is either referred to by פרק Perek
and הלכה, Halacha,
or actually it's by an עמוד, Amud, but an עמוד Amud based
in the original Venice printing, which actually has, I always found this
very strange because you will find sometimes a reference to ירושלמי Yerushalmi
of
like
דף סג עמוד ג. Daf Samech Gimel Amud Gimel. Now from the
בבלי Bavli perspective, an עמוד Amud is a side of a page.
So how can you have an עמוד ג, Amud Gimel, what you
have a three-dimensional page? But an עמוד Amud actually means a column.
So the way the בבלי Bavli is constructed, there's only one column
per page. The original, the one of the early printings of ירושלמי
Yerushalmi had two columns on each side of a page, so עמוד
ג Amud Gimel would be column three, which would be page B
column one, so it could go up to עמוד ד. Amud Dalet.
But anyway, we have it here, we will just use the בבלי
Bavli printing because that's also the way we're going to be organizing
ourselves. So I believe we take up on the top line of
ג עמוד א, Gimel Amud Aleph, so we're now at the second
stage of the משנה, Mishnah, which spoke about collecting the שקלים, Shekalim,
which is going to be the theme, but other things, and ראש
חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, so that the קרבנות Korbanot of each
year would come from a new collection each year.
And now we continue with מתקנין את הדרכים. Metaknin et hadrachim. It
should also be mentioned, you know, again, why do we have ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, why was this more relevant to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael than
it was, I mean, you know, than it was to בבל? Bavel?
So it should be mentioned that there was a regular tax that
the נשיא Nasi sort of supervised. I have to remind myself of
this, I learned this a long time ago when I took a
class in, you know, classical history, but anyway, but there was a
some type of a similar taxation that actually occurred under the Romans
each year, and that actually was also collected not just for the
Romans, but it was even collected from בבל, Bavel, from the
diaspora, for the sake of the Jewish community in ישראל. Yisrael. So
there is some type of a historical parallel to this מסכת Masechet
and the things that were actually happening, at least at the time
of the משנה, Mishnah, I don't know about at the time of
the גמרא ירושלמי. Gemara Yerushalmi. Anyway, if somebody here knows, we are
welcome to contribute that, if not, I'll try to refresh my memory
on that.
What was your parallel to the Romans?
There was a tax that actually was collected, I believe on an
annual basis, under the Romans. A, there was a Romans collected a
Jewish tax, number one. Number two, there was a tax that was
collected by the patriarch, you know, by the house of the נשיא,
Nasi, from the members of not only the Jews living in ישראל,
Yisrael, but even
the Jews.
Yeah, I'll try to remind myself of those and how whether it
continued into the time of the גמרא Gemara or not. But anyway,
it's worth noting just that there was some parallel there. I'll try
to get you some information on that tomorrow. Okay, so anyway, so
after we discussed the issue about collecting the tax, we now other
things that relate to אדר. Adar. So we mentioned about, of course,
the קריאת מגילה, Kriat Megilla,
and now it picks up at the top: מתקנין את הדרכים ואת
הרחובות ואת מקוואות המים ועושים כל צרכי הרבים. metaknin es haderachim ve’es
harechovot ve’es mikva’ot hamayim ve’osim kol tzorchei harabbim. So also in אדר
Adar you fix the roads and the alleys, presumably it's been a
rainy season now, it's becoming to be the spring, so you want
to clean everything up, especially also people hopefully are going to be
coming up לרגל, laregel, also coming up maybe to pay their שקלים.
shekalim.
And the מקוואות, mikvaot, which also got rains and are ruined, they
were sort of holes in the ground, they were not necessarily the
nice fancy מקוואות mikvaot that we have. Collecting rainwater? Yeah, but it's
not supposed to get all muddy and unusable. And you do all
the needs of the רבים. rabbim. Now we quote אלו הן צרכי
הרבים. eilu hein tzorchei harabbim. Now this is a משנה mishna in
מועד קטן Moed Katan that has nothing to do with us because
it's another use of the category of צרכי הרבים, tzorchei harabbim, but
in this context it's about things that can be done on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. On חול המועד Chol HaMoed you can do צרכי
הרבים. tzorchei harabbim. So this is not to be—it's quoted here because
of the parallel, but not to be assumed that the following list
are things you דווקא dafka did in אדר. Adar. Okay. דנים דיני
ממונות, danim dinei mamonot, these are things you can do on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. You can have a court, a civil court, hold
civil courts, ודיני נפשות, udinei nefashot, and courts about, you know, relating
to life issues, capital crimes, ודיני מכות, udinei makot, or lashes. So
you can run your court system on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. ופודים
ערכין וחרמין והקדשות. ufodin erchin vecharamin vehekdeshot.
You can do types of transactions that relate to the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. You can redeem things that have been, you know, that
you have sort of sanctified to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Difference
between ערך erech and חרם cherem and הקדש, hekdesh, we won't talk
about those distinctions right now. Well, okay, but anyway, there's different terms
you use. הקדש hekdesh sanctifies the object. חרם cherem is a little
bit of a question whether the object goes to the כהנים Kohanim
or to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ערכין erchin is if you
say the ערך erech of this person is on me and then
you pay a fixed value based on that person's age and gender.
So all those types of, anyway,
transactionary activities, but that relate to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash you're
allowed to do on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. ומשקין את הסוטה. umashkin
es hasota. That's interesting, right? Because maybe it deals with, I don't
know, erasing, you know, what exactly would be the concern why that
has to be mentioned other than, I mean, you know, maybe again
it assumes that קרבנות korbanos are taken for granted and these are
things that—it's a general question in terms of the גמרא Gemara when
we learn סוטה, Sota, how much of the גמרא Gemara tries to
incorporate סוטה Sota into a type of a דין din as opposed
to a ritual that's done in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
this is, you know, so it's interesting why that's singled out. ושורפין
את הפרה. usorfin es hapara. But it does seem here to be
in the context of things done in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
beyond קרבנות, korbanos, which presumably go without saying. You burn the פרה
אדומה para aduma if you have to get ashes.
ועורפין עגלה ערופה. veorfin egla arufa. You do an עגלה ערופה egla
arufa if you have to go out to a city and do
an עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, clearly that's of a communal concern.
ורוצעין עבד עברי. verotzin eved Ivri. Now that's interesting because that you
would think is a private person's concern to do the piercing of
the ear of an עבד עברי eved Ivri in order to make
him if he wants to be an עבד עולם. eved olam. So
I really don't know why that's considered to be a communal concern.
It wasn't done in the מקדש. Mikdash. Right. No, that's right. It's
interesting the shift. I mean the פרה para anyway was a מקדש
Mikdash related but it was then outside of the ground of the
מקדש. Mikdash. עגלה ערופה egla arufa certainly not. Right. So we're moving
outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. But the ורוצעין עבד עברי, verotzin eved
Ivri, I really don't know why. Again, obviously it does relate to,
you know, אשתו ואת בניו, ishto ve’es banav, so it relates to
him and his family as well, so it relates to other people,
not just you personally. And
but why that's considered a צרכי רבים, tzorchei rabbim, I don't know.
ומטהרין את המצורע. umetarin es hametzora. Okay. You do the טהרה tahara
process, not just the קרבנות, korbanos, which is again taken for granted,
of a מצורע. metzora. That presumably is a communal concern because you
don't want a מצורע metzora in your midst.
And it's not just about him privately. ומפרקין
את המנעל מעל גבי המאימר או האימום. umefarkin es haminal me’al gabei
hama’imar o ha’imum. Really? Now this is no longer part of the
משנה. mishna. This actually is a addition to the משנה mishna that's
added by a תוספתא Tosefta in מועד קטן. Moed Katan. And now
we're no longer talking about communal concerns. We're talking about מעשה הדיוט,
maaseh hedyot, things that are considered untrained labor as opposed to skilled
labor. So you can remove, if you have a shoe that's being
made and it's on like a horn, on a type of a
mold on which it's being sewn and made, and it's done, you
can remove it from that from that mold, from that horn. ואין
מחזירין אותה. ve’ein machzirin osah. Why מים mayim though? Yeah, what's the
wrong גירסא? girsa? So it's אימום. imum. Okay. ואין מחזירין אותה ve’ein
machzirin osah and you cannot restore it to that because that is
something that more requires craft. craftsmanship. Okay, so anyway, that's a list
of things you can do on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. It says,
I'm sorry, צרכי רבים, tzorkhei rabbim, but the גמרא Gemara actually is
quoting that, interestingly, it doesn't do anything with that משנה. Mishna. It
really is getting into another משנה Mishna about things you can do
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, so it's very strange that it starts
us with that משנה. Mishna. Here's another משנה Mishna of things you
can do on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, this is from the very
beginning of מועד קטן. Moed Katan. תמן תנינן, Taman teninan, over there
we taught, over there in מועד קטן Moed Katan we taught, משקין
בית השלחין Mashkin beit hashalachin ומציינין
את הקברות. umetzaynin et hakevarot. You
can irrigate irrigated fields, those that need it and that if you
don't irrigate them they'll dry up, and you can designate where there
are graves, you can put gravestones and other types of paint and
designation so כהנים Kohanim don't come טמא. tamei. All these you can
do on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. And the third line there is,
which is cut out, but the גמרא Gemara will quote later is
where is it? It's quoted somewhere here. Hold on.
What's the third line? The third line is a minute,
I think it's quoted in the קרבן העדה, Korban HaEdah, one minute,
ויוצאין אף על הכלאים במועד veyotzin af al hakilayim bamoed was the
end of the משנה. Mishna. Okay, so you designate the קברות kevarot
and ויוצאין על הכלאים, veyotzin al hakilayim, you send people out to
uproot כלאים kilayim if they're growing in the field, and you do
that on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So those two, מציינין את הקברות
ויוצאין על הכלאים, metzaynin et hakevarot veyotzin al hakilayim, is exactly what
we mention in our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna says, right, the
end of our משנה Mishna is עושין כל צרכי הרבים ומציינין את
הקברות ויוצאין אף על הכלאים. osin kol tzorkhei harabbim umetzaynin et hakevarot
veyotzin af al hakilayim. So exactly those two is the ones that's
mentioned in the beginning of מועד קטן. Moed Katan. So the line
in our משנה Mishna of עושין כל צרכי הרבים, osin kol tzorkhei
harabbim, it quotes this whole משנה Mishna צרכי רבים tzorkhei rabbim for
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. But why? It's unclear whether by quoting that
משנה, Mishna, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi means to suggest that these are all
the activities you do starting on ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar.
Why דוקא davka you have to say you do these? These are
activities you do throughout the year. So again, quoting this משנה Mishna
about צרכי רבים tzorkhei rabbim is unclear, but now we're looking at
the end of our משנה Mishna and making another parallel to מועד
קטן Moed Katan where the end of our משנה Mishna speaks about
the graves and the כלאים kilayim and that's exactly what the first
משנה מועד קטן Mishna Moed Katan talks about, that you go out
to designate graves and pull out כלאים kilayim on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. There's a big problem that from אדר Adar to חול המועד
Chol HaMoed is a month. So if you did it in אדר,
Adar, why do you have to do it on חול המועד? Chol
HaMoed? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask those two questions about the כלאים kilayim and the קברות.
kevarot. Okay, so let's take a look. So it says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא כבר ציינו מאדר? lo kevar tzeinu
me'Adar? I don't understand why you have to designate the graves. Didn't
you already do it in אדר? Adar?
So it says all
right, תיפתר, tipatar, you can explain
it שירד שטף של גשמים ושטפה, sheyarad shetef shel geshamim veshafah, that
a, you know, a downpouring of rain came down and it wiped
away the designation. You know, they might have designated it also with
like
lye and types of like, you know, white paint. So therefore, if
it's very rainy, it washes that away. It could also be, as
we'll see, it washes away, you know, graves, gravestones as well. So
that's the case, yes, it was a rainy season and the rain
had not finished and even though you did in אדר, Adar, you
might have to do it again around חול המועד ניסן Chol HaMoed
Nisan in the middle of חול המועד פסח Chol HaMoed Pesach in
the middle of
ניסן.
Nisan. Yes, תיפתר, tipatar, a בבלי Bavli term?
No, it's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi term. No, it's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi term.
I'm trying to think of exactly what the בבלי Bavli analog is.
But it means you can explain it in the following way. Right,
like תתרץ, titaretz, you know, or or תפתור, tiphtor, right, לפטור, liftor,
to explain, like תרגמו אותה ככה. tirgemu otah kakhah.
That's clearly what the word means but it's not right, I was
just trying to think what the analog is.
It's maybe sort of like הכא במאי עסקינן hakha bemai askinan might
be some type of a thing. הכא במאי עסקינן hakha bemai askinan
is very specifically like trying to create a circumstantial context for it.
I think תיפתר tipatar is similar to that. Okay, but it's similar
to the בבלי's Bavli הכא במאי עסקינן. hakha bemai askinan. All right,
so right, לפטור liftor means to explain, to interpret it the following
way.
Strange though that usually by the middle of ניסן, Nisan, by פסח
Pesach the rainy season is over.
Right, but if you're off in the calendar and you haven't adjusted
it correctly yet, which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to say
in a minute, there could be times when that's going to be
a need and that's what we're going to deal with also in
terms of the כלאים. kilayim. So let's take a look. ויוצאין אף
על הכלאים במועד. veyotzin af al hakilayim bamoed. So this is the
end of that משנה Mishna in מועד קטן. Moed Katan. לא כבר
יצאו מאדר? lo kevar yatzu me'Adar? Didn't they go out in אדר?
Adar? Because if people had, you know, basically the point of the
כלאים kilayim seemed to be not necessarily that people are consciously planting
כלאים, kilayim, but people aren't being conscientious enough to uproot errant seeds
that might have fallen into their field and they're, you know, and
they're going to now plant whatever wheat and they weren't paying attention
that they dropped grape seed and now you have these little grape
sprouts coming up. The בית דין Beis Din would send out people
to inspect it and to weed it, and we'll see about the
implications of that in a minute. So didn't they already do that
in אדר? Adar? תיפתר שהיה השנה אפילה Tiphtar she'haya hashana afeila ואין
הצמחים ניכרים. ve'ein hatzmachim nikarim. So the year was אפילה, afeila, which
could mean dark, okay, which means that it was
still a rainy season, it could mean also that again the calendar
was off, so the days still were not getting longer yet because
the calendar wasn't totally in sync and you could not see the
sprouts, maybe because it was so dark, but it's probably hard to
imagine it was so dark all the time. Some want to read
אפילה afeila as late, like כי ה- מה זה? כי השעורה אביב
והגבעה כי אפילתנה,
ki ha- mah zeh? Ki hase'orah aviv vehagiva
ki afeilosena, right, which means late to sprout, which means that it
was a late year in the sense again that the calendar was
off, so even though it was אדר Adar time, it was really
earlier in the winter, you know, they had not fully adjusted the
calendar, so the spring had not yet arrived by ניסן Nissan and
only by the ניסן Nissan time was it beginning to be the
warmer season and only then were the sprouts coming out. Okay, so
that's how we explain our משנה, Mishnah, why you do it in
אדר Adar and why you might have to do it again in
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Our משנה Mishnah says צרכי רבים, tzorchei rabbim,
there's the צרכי רבים tzorchei rabbim in מועד קטן, Moed Katan, hard
to imagine that it's really the same thing. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
really elaborate on צרכי רבים tzorchei rabbim anymore. Now because we mentioned
designating graves, the גמרא Gemara focuses on that for a little bit.
מניין לציון, Minaiyan l'tziyun, right, ציון tziyun זיין. zayin. How do you
know that, how do you know you're supposed to designate graves? רב
רחי רב יעקב בר בת יעקב, Rav Rachi Rav Yaakov bar Bas
Yaakov, the son of the daughter of Yaakov, interesting, בשם רב חוניא
דברת חברין, beshem Rav Chunya de'Bras Chavrin, in the name of רב
חוניא Rav Chunya from this place of ברת חברין, Bras Chavrin, or
רב יוסה
אמרה לה, Rav Yosa amrah lah, if רב יוסי Rav Yosi says
it's רב יעקב בר
אחא.
Rav Yaakov
bar Acha.
My גירסא girsa says רב יוסי, Rav Yosi, רב יוסה, Rav Yosa,
I thought it said רב יוסה. Rav Yosa. רב יוסה אמרה לה
רב יעקב בר אחא, Rav Yosa amrah lah Rav Yaakov bar Acha,
it's not רב יעקב בר בת יעקב, Rav Yaakov bar Bas Yaakov,
it's רב יעקב בר אחא Rav Yaakov bar Acha בשם חוניא דברת
חברין. beshem Chunya de'Bras Chavrin. So a different אמורא Amora in the
name of רב חוניא Rav Chunya from בת חברין. Bas Chavrin. רב
חזקיה רב עוזיאל בריה דרב חוניא דבת חברין, Rav Chizkiya Rav Uziel
brei de'Rav Chunya de'Bas Chavrin, and רב חזקיה Rav Chizkiya says it's
רב עוזיאל Rav Uziel the son of רב חוניא Rav Chunya from
בית חוברין, Beis Chovrin, so everybody says it's בת חוברין, Bas Chovrin,
בית חוברין, Beis Chovrin, ברת חוברין. Bras Chovrin. נחל חברים. Nachal Chaverim.
בשם רב חוניא דבית חוברין, beshem Rav Chunya de'Beis Chovrin, in the
name of רב חוניא Rav Chunya for בית חוברין, Beis Chovrin, so
very fascinating. I don't know, right exactly, all these different names, I
don't know where בית חוברין Beis Chovrin is. נחל חברים. Nachal Chaverim.
Is there?
Spelled just like
that. Interesting. By the Dead Sea.
It's by the Dead Sea. Fascinating. נחל חברים.
Nachal
Chaverim. It's actually no, I take it back, it's שדה בוקר. Sde
Boker. It's in the middle of the נגב. Negev. It's right near
שדה בוקר. Sde Boker.
Okay, very nice. So the תנא Tanna is probably from that place.
Anyway, what's the statement? וטמא טמא יקרא. V'tamei tamei yikra. Tamei tamei
they will call out. That's by the
מצורע. Metzora. So what does that mean? It means כדי שתהא הטומאה
קוראה בפיה. kedei shetehei hatumah koreiah befiha. So the טומאה tumah itself
calls out to you. The טומאה tumah announces itself. And so to
stay away. Okay, presumably that's the idea of וטמא טמא יקרא v'tamei
tamei yikra by the מצורע. metzora. Stay away. And here it means
it's explained by all טומאה. tumah. All טומאה tumah should call out
to you and announce itself so that you should know to stay
away. ואומרת לך פרוש. Veomeret lach perosh. Separate, stay away. רב אילא
בשם רב שמואל בר נחמן Rav Ila beshem Rav Shmuel bar Nachman
says ועברו העוברים בארץ וראה עצם אדם. v'avru ha'ovrim ba'aretz vera'ah etzem
adam. People will pass through the land and they'll see a bone
of a man
ובנה אצלו ציון. uvanah etzlo tziyun. I did it again. And they
will build by it a marker. Okay, now that is according to
the פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim is a marker in order
to then move the bone, but from here we see the idea
of making a marker by a
grave. עצם. Etzem. מכאן שמציינין על העצמות. mikan she'metzaynin al ha'atzamos. So
bone is to tell you that you make markers by where there
are bones. The reason to emphasize bones here is number one, two
things. As we're going to see, if there's only human flesh and
no bones, you would not make a marker because the flesh would
decompose, and markers is for stuff that's going to be there for
a long time. Number two is the basic concern of markers is
that כהנים Kohanim should not walk nearby and be over it and
become טמא. tamei. So it's only things that cause טומאה באהל. tumah
b'ohel. So even bones if you have enough bones, not small amount,
but if you have enough bones, they will cause טומאה tumah in
you know by being over them. So you make it over bones.
אדם. Adam. The bone of a man. מכאן שמציינין על השדרה ועל
הגולגולת. mikan she'metzaynin al hashidrah v'al hagulgoles. Anything that sort of represents
the human being. So it would be the spine and the skull
because that would even be single bones that would cause that would
cause טומאה באהל. tumah b'ohel.
The skull isn't part of עצם? etzem?
Well, the point is by bones you need a certain quantity to
cause טומאה באהל. tumah b'ohel. Here it's even those as a single
bone. Again, it's an אסמכתא, asmachta, okay, but it means the type
of bones that would cause טומאה באהל, tumah b'ohel, either it's a
quantity or it's the skull and the and the spine etc. ובנה.
Uvanah. You should build a marker on
it. מכאן שמציינין שמציינין על גבי אבן קבועה. mikan she'metzaynin שמציינין mikan
she'metzaynin al gabei even kevuah. It's not so much על גבי, al
gabei, but
here... Not just put a stone. Not just put a stone down
on it. No, it has to be something that's dug in the
ground, that's built there, that's going to stay there. Okay. Why? For
an obvious reason. אם אומר את על גבי אבן תלושה, Im omer
at al gabei even telushah, if your marker, now it could mean
actually not that you put a stone like we do, like we
actually take a stone, we carve it, we write something on it,
we make a gravestone, it might mean the phrase of על גבי
אבן al gabei even is again, you might be coming with your
lime or whatever it is, you know, lime is that white stone,
right? Your lime and you'll make a mark on a stone. Here's
the grave, here's a nearby stone. I didn't put the stone there.
I'm going to make a mark on that stone. Okay, but if
you're going to make a mark on a stone, make it on
a permanent stone, not on a stone that can easily be moved,
because then the stone will move away and the mark will move
away. So, אם אומר את על גבי אבן תלושה, Im omer at
al gabei even telushah, if you're going to make your marker on
top of a movable
stone, אף היא הולכת ומטמאת במקום אחר, af hi holechet u-metamet be-makom
acher, it'll go and cause tumah elsewhere, not literally cause tumah, but
make you identify a wrong place as being טמא, tamei, right? As
opposed to the right place being טמא. tamei. So if you're going
to make a mark, you've got to make it on something that's
going to be in a fixed location. אצלו Etzlo nearby, right? So
it doesn't say you build on it a marker, you build near
it a marker. למקום טהרה ציון. Le-makom taharah tziyun. You have to
make the marker in the non-tamei space. So you don't want to
be atop of the grave and then realize there's a marker. You
want the marker a little bit before you get to the danger
area. So that's near it is the marker, not on top of
it. Okay. למקום טהרה? Le-makom taharah? No, למקום טהרה ציון, le-makom taharah
tziyun, a marker. מכאן לציון, Mi-kan le-tziyun, here you see the mark
I mean that we've been talking about all along. Okay, so that's
how we interpret each word of that פסוק. pasuk. ומצא. U-matza. I'm
sorry, so that's the end of the פסוק. pasuk. I'm starting to
switch the gear so as you have seen in all these sort
of little notes, the גרסא girsa in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is less
fixed than that of the בבלי Bavli or less stable, less certain.
Part of it has to do with the fact that it was
learned less, so there are very, very few manuscripts. We really only
have one full manuscript of the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Other than that, we
just have tiny little pieces. So one wonders, you know, what would
have been the fate of this entire work if that one manuscript
had been lost. Now, it doesn't mean that there was only one
manuscript throughout history. It means of all the manuscripts that there were,
only one actually survived: the Leiden manuscript of the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. There's
actually a we have downstairs, Sussmann's edition that
yeah, so there's this huge red ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the whole thing in
one volume where they did a complete new transcription from that one
manuscript. Okay, but it doesn't mean just because it's the one manuscript
that it's accurate, it's just the one full manuscript we have, then
we have little pieces of it. So there's often a question of
the גרסא. girsa. Now sometimes the reason that the גרסא girsa is
changed is because people didn't understand the exact Aramaic of the ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, so they'll switch the גרסא girsa to make more sense to
them, or because, you know, they didn't understand just, you know, what
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was doing, so again, you switch it to you
massage it to make it make more sense. But sometimes actually there
is a question of the actual correct גרסא. girsa. So here, ומצא
u-matza does not seem to be a continuation. It seems actually to
be a new point of now a new הלכה. halacha. Now that
we're done with the פסוקים pesukim of מכאן לציון mi-kan le-tziyun and
so on, that we know you build it, now we're talking about
when you actually find a marker, what assumptions you're supposed to make.
So let's take a look. ומצא אבן אחת מצויינת, U-matza even achat
metzuyenet, if you find one stone that is sort of marked, אף
על
פי שאין מקיימין כן, af al pi she-ein mekayamin ken, even though
you don't put it there, meaning you don't have markers, as we
said, directly on top of the מת. met. You have them nearby.
Nevertheless, you have to be concerned that maybe somebody actually did it
directly over the מת. met. So if you actually went and leaned
over a marker, you can't assume, oh, I'm safe, markers are always
away from the מת. met. No, אף על פי שאין מקיימין כן,
af al pi she-ein mekayamin ken, even though you don't keep it
that way and establish it that way over the מת, met, המאהיל
עליה טמא. ha-ma'ahil aleha tamei. You still have to assume you're טמא
tamei if you leaned over it, walked over it. אני אומר מת
מצויין והיה נתון תחתיה. Ani omer met metzuyan ve-hayah natun tachteha. Again,
some sketchy גרסא girsa from מת מצויין, met metzuyan, but it means
that the the מת met was like sort of maybe, you know,
folded over and maybe it was directly underneath the marker. So although
the marker should be away from the מת, met, you can't assume
you're safe once you bump into the marker and once you go
over the marker.
So the markers you're talking about are on top of the grave,
because we tend to think of stones or something like that, but
I also understand they're talking about lime.
Yeah, that's a lime. I was saying lye. I meant lime.
Right, but this is more like a powder kind of marking the
ground itself.
And that's how it can wash away. Right. It did talk about
stones. Right. It did talk about stones, but it's not like you
take a gravestone and you carve a gravestone. You use the sort
of terrain that you have in front of you and you take
this lime. Lime or lime? Lime. Lime. L-Y-E. L-Y-E like lye soap.
L-I-M-E that's the סיד sid in English. Lime. Okay, not lye.
Okay, I was saying lye, but it's lime.
Anyway, right, you take this and you basically like paint, I imagine
like white marks around the graves, or on the stones nearby. I
right, but here we see it's supposed to be a little bit
removed from the grave
so you're not on top of the grave by the time you
hit it.
But we all rely
on that, it could be. Right, then that's the irony that when
you actually do hit it, we're going to miss you coming anyway
because if we're, you know, we're understanding this correctly. I will say
it's fascinating that the only idea of marking graves is about a
concern of טומאה. tumah. There's no idea that like you want to
know, you want to remember where your, you know, where your parents
are buried, you want to be able to go there for a
יארצייט, yahrzeit, you know, this idea, it's fascinating. You know, we've, our
approach towards the מתים metim and in the גמרא, Gemara, it's all
about a טומאה tumah concern. Yes.
So to want a short technical question on the פסוק, pasuk, is
there, was there an indicator like in the בבלי Bavli דכתיב de-chtiv
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, was there any indicator that a פסוק pasuk was now
being quoted? Please.
Oh yeah, that's a good point. In the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi does that less and actually yesterday also it just started quoting
פסוקים, psukim, it never said שנאמר she-ne'emar or כתיב. ktiv. I don't
know if it never does it, but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi very often,
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi introduces text, whether it's a פסוק, pasuk, whether it's
a תוספתא, Tosefta, without any introduction.
And that makes it difficult.
Right, it doesn't signal where, right. Like this point here about מצבה
אבן אחת, Matzeva Even Achat, you know, I believe some say that
that's a, I believe some say it's a ברייתא Baraita and it's
a תוספתא. Tosefta.
It's a תוספתא, Tosefta, right.
So if it's quoting a תוספתא, Tosefta, we don't even know that
it did the shift. Yes, you look in the מסורת הש"ס, Masoret
HaShas, it says that that's a תוספתא Tosefta and we don't even
know that it did the shift. So you're right, not only the
פסוקים, psukim, any introduction of text is often done without a signaling.
But this last idea that you just read, that's similar to the
statement, I forget where it's from, but "אין מציינין למתים כבצידן של
חכמים כי מעשיהן ציוניהם". Ein metzaynin la-metim ke-v-tzidan shel chachamim ki ma'aseihen
tziyuneihem. Right, exactly. Not the נפש, nefesh, on the word נפש, nefesh,
נפשותיהם, nafshoteihem, the
נפש nefesh is a ציון. tziyun. Right. So this seems to have
not been the practice of visiting.
Although, they did have those family grave sites where they buried them
in those כוכים, kuchim, in the caves, and whatever, that
was the royal family as well. So, right, so it is quite
interesting though that clearly, you know, the focus on going to the
graves of family members was very different, did not seem to be
so strong. Okay, so let's keep on going. The source said that
like, you know,
most of the time, you know, it wasn't the case and you'd
have to mark.
Right, so they'd have to know.
Even someone with maybe no family, maybe it was like, you know,
the person who was
killed, sort of like, sort of like פרשת עגלה ערופה Parashat Eglah
Arufah or something, it was not somebody that had a family grave.
Right, yeah, that's a possibility too. Okay, היו שתים, Hayu shtayim, now
if there were two stones that were marked, המונח עליהן טהור וביניהן
טמא. Ha-monach aleihen tahor u-vineihen tamei. You can assume, if it's only
one stone, and this was why you have to be חושש choshesh
for the one stone, because where's the whole circumference? So maybe if
it's only one stone, the מת met is directly under it. But
if it's two stones, then you assume that's marking the, you know,
the space between the two stones. So then you can assume that
the stones themselves are okay and it's the space between them that
is a problem. So as long as you have a clear area
marked off, you can assume that the actual marked stones are
okay. Now, where were we? היה חרוש Haya charush or חורש choresh
בינתיים, be-ntayim, if the space between the two stones was plowed, then
you've got a problem because you presumably would not plow where there
was a grave. הרי הן כיחידות, Harey hen ki-yechidot, and then the
stones are like two individual stones. ביניהן טהור, Beinehem tahor, the space
between them is
okay, וסביבותיהן טמא, u-svivoteihen tamei, right directly around them, meaning under them
and maybe nearby, you know, in a little bit of an expanded
circumference is טמא tamei because again, they're not marking off an area
so you assume that the מת met is directly underneath. תני, Tani,
we taught a ברייתא. Baraita. So here we introduce it as a
ברייתא, Baraita, right? אין מציינין על הבשר, Ein metzaynin al ha-basar, you
do not make a marker over just human flesh that does not
have a bone. שמא יתאכל הבשר, Shema yitakel ha-basar, lest the flesh
be decomposed and it won't, the marker's more permanent. So that's okay,
but so what, at least you'll be safe. So let's take a
look. רבי יוסי בר אבון Rabbi Yose bar Abun בעא קומי ba'ei
kumi רבי מנא. Rabbi Mana. רבי יוסי בר אבון Rabbi Yose bar
Abun asked in front of רבי מנא. Rabbi Mana. ולא נמצא מטמא
טהרות למפרע? Velo nimtza metamei teharot le-mafrea? Won't you wind up making
טמא, tamei, you know, being מטמא metamei things that are טהור tahor
למפרע? le-mafrea? Because you're not going to, the word למפרע le-mafrea is
a little funny, but the point is you're not going to mark
it. So at a later time it'll be טהור. tahor. But in
the interim, there'll still be human flesh there, and somebody will become
טמא, tamei, and it won't be marked, and he'll go ahead and
be טמא tamei and not be aware that he's טמא. tamei. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, מוטב שיתקלקלו בו לשעה ואל יתקלקלו בו לעולם. Mutav
she-yitkalkelu vo la-sha'ah ve-al yitkalkelu vo le-olam. It's a very powerful phrase.
I'd rather that there be a period of time where it leads
to error and that people actually are טמא tamei and they think
they're טהור tahor than for all future times it be an error
and that, you know, for... Permanently, people are going to think that
they're טמא tamei when they really are טהור tahor and the fascinating
thing is that he's actually willing to allow, meaning he wants to
do that to save from an unnecessary חומרא. chumra. Right? Let people
think, oh, people, what does he מחמיר? machmir? Let people think they're
always טמא. tamei. So what? It's just a חומרא. chumra. No, he
doesn't want to create that type of an unnecessary חומרא chumra for
a long period of time and he'd rather be allowing people to
actually be more מקל meikel than is appropriate, think they're טהור tahor
when they're טמא. tamei. So that's quite a fascinating state. Let's look
at the next משנה. Mishna. משנה. Mishna. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav
Yehuda. בראשונה היו עוקרין ומשליכין לפניהם. Barishona hayu okrin umashlichin lifneihem. I
should also mention by the idea, not like it's particularly relevant here,
but we don't know the משנה Mishna that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was
referring to, meaning in the most texts of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi משנה
Mishna they just take a text of a משנה Mishna from some
other משנה Mishna text. But sometimes part of we have a hard
time understanding the ירושלמי Yerushalmi because we don't realize that the text
of the משנה Mishna they had was actually different than the one
that's printed with the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So just to be aware. If
the גמרא Gemara when they comment on it, is it commenting on
a different text?
Yeah, the printer just
took a משנה Mishna and slapped it here. But the actual ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, the one manuscript we have, had the גמרא Gemara but didn't
have the משנה. Mishna. So we don't exactly know which what was
its exact text of the משנה Mishna that it was commenting on.
Okay. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, so said רב יהודה. Rav
Yehuda. בראשונה היו עוקרין ומשליכין לפניהם. Barishona hayu okrin umashlichin lifneihem. Now
when they're going out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, originally they would uproot the
sprouts of כלאים kilayim and throw it in front of the owners.
משרבו עוברי עבירה Mishe-rabu ovrei aveira when the sinners increased, היו משליכין
לדרכים, hayu mashlichim ladrahin, they threw it out into the roads. התקינו,
Hitkinu, then they established, היו מפקירים את כל השדה, hayu mafkirim es
kol hasadeh, that if people had כלאים kilayim growing in the field
they would make the whole field ownerless and come and seize the
field or seize all what's growing in the field. So let's take
a look at what this history is about. אמר רב יהודה, Amar
Rav Yehuda, תני, tani, we taught in a ברייתא. Baraita. אמר רב
יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, בראשונה היו עוקרין ומשליכין לפניהם. Barishona hayu okrin
umashlichin lifneihem. They would uproot and throw it. והיו שמחים שיש מוכה.
Vehayu smeichim sheis mocheh. The owners of the fields would be very
happy. אחת שהיו מנכשים שדותיהם. Achas shehayu menachshin sadeihem. One is that
the בית דין Beis Din is coming and weeding their field. Right?
It just encourages sloppy behavior. If I know בית דין Beis Din
is going to come along and remove all the errant sprouts, so
wonderful, I'm not going to bother doing it myself, they'll come and
take care of it. ואחת שהיו נהנין מן הכלאים. Ve-achas shehayu nehenin
min ha-kilayim. Then they would throw those sprouts out and I'd feed
it to my animals and I'd get benefit, which is, you know,
now if you can get הנאה hana'ah from כלאים kilayim if it's
not כלאי הכרם, kilei hakerem, but anyway, still it would be inappropriate.
Look at all the benefit they would get for actually not being
careful about כלאים. kilayim. משרבו עוברי עבירה, Mishe-rabu ovrei aveira, so once
that increased and it just led to worse behavior, היו משליכין על
הדרכים. hayu mashlichim al hadrahim. They would throw it on the road.
אף על פי כן, Af al pi kein, and even so, so
that prevented them from actually feeding it to their animals. היו שמחים,
Hayu smeichim, they would still be happy אחת שהיו מנכשים שדותיהם achas
shehayu menachshin sadeihem that the בית דין Beis Din would actually be
uprooting the, would be weeding their field. התקינו שיהו מפקירים כל השדה
כולה. Hitkinu sheyehe mafkirin kol hasadeh kullah. So then they decided if
this is the problem, now they might still have uprooted the כלאים,
kilayim, they don't want כלאים kilayim growing, but they're going to fine
you if you allowed this to happen and they'll make the whole
שדה sadeh הפקר, hefker, which I don't know again means whether people
could actually seize the land or just seize the crops, but there
was going to be an actual real negative consequence to this. There
actually is a phenomenon like this, I'm trying to remember what it's
called, I had an NPR piece about it like a month ago
where, you know, the government tries to create some type of thing
to deal with a problem and it actually has the exact opposite
effect. Like they tried to sort of say like
they did something with the farmers like if, you know, for every
because the pigs were destroying the field, so every pig that's killed,
a wild pig, you go ahead and you know they get a
bounty on it. And of course what that just led to is
people raising the wild pigs in order to get the bounty.
So there's actually like a name for this type of a phenomenon
where it actually engenders the exact opposite behavior that you're trying to
address. Okay. So
anyway,
now that we said that בית דין Beis Din would make the
whole field הפקר, hefker, that leads us into a classic discussion in
the בבלי Bavli and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi of הפקר בית דין הפקר.
hefker Beis Din hefker. מנין שהפקר בית דין הפקר? Minayin she-hefker Beis
Din hefker?
Where do you know that things that בית דין Beis Din makes
ownerless that that is effective? דכתיב, De-chsiv, because it says, and this
is specifically in the context like it is here in the משנה
Mishna of imposing a קנס, knas, a fine, of actually, you know,
sort of using the sort of
the regulatory, not regulatory, the punishing authority of בית דין. Beis Din.
וכל אשר לא יבוא לשלשת הימים, Ve-chol asher lo yavo lishloshes yamim,
this is by עזרא Ezra in ספר עזרא Sefer Ezra when they
were trying to call everybody together, anybody who doesn't come within three
days, בעצת השרים והזקנים, ba-atzas hasarim vehazkeinim, based on the sort of
ruling, advice of the charged, of the elders, יחרם כל רכושו, yachoram
kol rechusho, all of their property will be banned, והוא יבדל מקהל
הגולה, vehu yibadel mikhal hagola, and
this person will be driven out of the community. So they understand
יחרם כל רכושו yachoram kol rechusho means that you no longer own
your property and then presumably anybody can come and take it. So
again, that's very much in the context of a קנס, knas, of
a fine. And that's the context of this משנה. mishna. It is
worth noting that the בבלי Bavli uses הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker
beis din hefker many times not for a קנס knas but just
normal תקנות takanos of בית דין beis din in order to deal,
give בית דין beis din power in civil areas, uses that, but
that's not the immediate context of this פסוק pasuk or of this
משנה. mishna. Okay, now מנין שפטור מן המעשרות. minayin shepatur min hama'asros.
If you say that the field is הפקר, hefker, then הפקר hefker
grain is not obligated in מעשרות, ma'asros, people can take it. How
do you know that this idea is so powerful that it actually
exempts the grain from מעשר? ma'aser? Now to me that's a funny
question because once it's הפקר hefker it's הפקר hefker and all the
natural consequences of הפקר hefker should apply. But let's take a look.
רב יונתן בריה דרב יצחק בר אחא שמע לה מן הדא. Rav
Yonatan brei deRav Yitzchak bar Acha shama lah min hada. So רב
יונתן Rav Yonatan hears it from the following. People often point out
by the way that there's a fascinating difference that the בבלי Bavli
when it introduces a text says תא שמע, ta shma, come and
hear, and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says תא חזי, ta chazi, come and
see. So, difference about how you talk about like how you learn,
how you encounter new material, encounter it, you hear something or see
something. But of course the ירושלמי Yerushalmi also uses hear: שמע לה
מן הדא, shama lah min hada, he hears it from here, so
it is interesting though to note that verb, the use of those
verbs. אין מעברין את השנה לא בשביעית ולא במוצאי שביעית. ein ma'avrin
es hashana lo bishvi'is velo bemotzei shvi'is. You do not make an
עיבור ibbur year, add a month, if it's a שמיטה shmittah year
because you don't want to stretch out שמיטה shmittah another month, it's
a hardship, and not in a מוצאי שביעית. motzei shvi'is. Why? Because
מוצאי שביעית motzei shvi'is you need all the grain that you've been
growing, the new grain that you're growing, and if you add a
month, you add the month before ניסן, Nisan, you add it in
אדר, Adar, and that's going to take another month before the עומר
Omer is brought and before you can benefit from the grain. Okay,
so you don't make an עיבור ibbur year. ואם עיברוה הרי זו
מעוברת. ve'im ibruha harei zu me'uberes. So that, then it does work.
So you see בית דין beis din can add a month to
שמיטה. shmittah. וחודש אחד שהוא מוסיף לא פטור מן המעשרות? vechodesh echad
shehu mosif lo patur min hama'asros? So when you add a month
to שמיטה, shmittah, then that month, anything that grows in that extra
month is going to be exempt, so you see בית דין beis
din when they, their power actually can make things exempt from מעשר,
ma'aser, which is such a
bizarre
proof which the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. That's because they
made it a שמיטה shmittah year, that's because they have the power
to
add a month to the year, it's not a direct act of
הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker. But בית דין beis
din thinks that it's just too late of a spring, so they,
even though it's שמיטה, shmittah, they still really feel like they shouldn't
do an עיבור. ibbur. Correct, they'll do an extra month. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: עד כדון שביעית, ad kadon shvi'is,
now מוצאי שביעית מה? motzei shvi'is mah? So we understand why they
don't make the extra extra month in שביעית. shvi'is. Why don't they
make it, עד כה ad koh or whatever, why don't they make
it in מוצאי שביעית? motzei shvi'is? אמר רבי אבון רבי בון, amar
Rebbi Avun Rebbi Bon, שלא להרבות בחדש חדש. shelo leharbos bechadash chadash.
Like I told you, not to make the prohibition of חדש chadash
last an extra month when everybody desperately needs the grain, it's מוצאי
שביעית. motzei shvi'is. רבי זירא בשם רבי אלעזר Rebbi Zeira beshem Rebbi
Elazar says, or רבי אבהו, Rebbi Abbahu, again, question of exactly the
גרסא, girsa, הדא דאת אמר, hada de'at amar, so when is this
true? עד שלא התיר רבי להביא ירק מחוץ לארץ. ad shelo hitir
Rebbe lehavi yarak michutz la'aretz. When רבי Rebbe
still held the prohibition of bringing vegetables from חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz.
There's all these interesting things in the time of רבי Rebbe in
the time of משנה mishna about things related to חוץ לארץ, chutz
la'aretz, that the ground of חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz was טמא. tamei.
Some of these things had to do with concerns of טומאה, tumah,
some of these things had to do with, according to some historians
and academics, about תקנות takanos that were supporting, exactly, the local industry
of ישראל. Yisrael. So רבי Rebbe did not want you to import
any vegetables from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, A to maybe support local
industry, B it would come with the dirt of חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz where there were טומאה tumah concerns and so on. Right, but
then he loosened up on that and let people bring in vegetables.
אבל משהתיר רבי להביא ירק מחוץ לארץ, aval mishehitir Rebbe lehavi yarak
michutz la'aretz, היא שביעית היא של שאר שני שבוע. hi shvi'is hi
shel she'ar shenei shavua. You can add a month to שמיטה, shmittah,
it won't be such a hardship
because you can just go ahead and continue to eat imported vegetables.
So the whole idea of the hardships of שמיטה shmittah and the
use of, here importing vegetables during the שמיטה shmittah year and so
on is something that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was well aware of. Okay,
תני אין מעברין. tani ein ma'avrin. Now we're going to finish this
point about not adding a month in מוצאי שביעית. motzei shvi'is. אמר
רב מנא הדא דאת אמר בראשונה שהיו השנים כתקנן. amar Rav Mana
hada de'at amar barishona shehayu hashanim ketiknan.
That was way in the beginning when the years were the way
they should have been. Okay, אבל עכשיו שאינן השנים כתקנן. aval achshav
she'einan hashanim ketiknan.
Now that the years are not their way they should be, we'll
talk about what that means in a minute. היא שביעית היא של
שאר שני שבוע. hi shvi'is hi shel she'ar shenei shavua. The same
is שמיטה, shmittah, the same is the other years. What does that
mean? So some say it means when we really had a בית
דין beis din and we had יובל Yovel and we had שמיטה
shmittah the way we're supposed to have our שמיטה shmittah years, then
שמיטה shmittah was נוהג noheg and you couldn't add a month to
the year. But nowadays, when maybe שמיטה shmittah isn't done at all,
or maybe it's only
דרבנן, derabanan, post חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, this is one way of
reading it, then שמיטה shmittah maybe isn't נוהג noheg nowadays and you
can add a month to the year. There's a big problem reading
it that way is that שמיטה shmittah is נוהג noheg nowadays, it's
true there's a debate whether it's biblical or rabbinic, but it's very
hard to read it like oh שמיטה shmittah doesn't matter so much
nowadays. So others have the גרסא girsa not היא ששביעית hi sheshvi'is
but היא של מוצאי שביעית, hi shel motzei shvi'is, היא של שאר
שני שבוע. hi shel she'ar shenei shavua.
We've already explained why you can add a month to שמיטה Shemita
because you're allowed to import vegetables. And now we're explaining why you
can add a month to מוצאי שמיטה. Motzei Shemita. Why? Because you're
saying now our years are all screwed up. What does it mean
our years are all screwed up? Now, if we have to add
a month to a year, going back to the theme beforehand, it's
because we're still in the middle of winter. So by adding a
month, we're not postponing eating the grain. If we're adding a month,
it's because the grain won't be ready for a month. And so
therefore we do it, when we do it now, we do it
for a reason that is that makes it acceptable even מוצאי שמיטה.
Motzei Shemita.
Now you can ask the same question as before.
Yeah, I was going to, I was waiting for that question before
also, you know, even if they also added it when it was
necessary, so I don't know the exact answer. All right, now the
גמרא Gemara gets back to, it's interesting, it's completely digressed. It's put
out there the proof of this that בית דין Beit Din makes
something פטור pattur from מעשרות Maasrot because they add a month to
שמיטה. Shemita. And now it gets back and says why it wasn't
a good proof. So let's take a look. אמר רבי אבון, Amar
Rabbi Avon, רבי אבון Rabbi Avon said, אין מן הדא, In min
hada, if if that's your proof, that בית דין Beit Din can
make something פטור pattur from מעשרות Maasrot
because they can add a month to שמיטה, Shemita, לית את שמיע
מינה כלום. Leit at shemia mineh klum. You can't hear anything from
it, meaning you can't, that's not a proof at all. Why is
that not a proof at all? שמור את חודש האביב Shamor et
chodesh ha'aviv because their role in adding a month to the year
is based on a פסוק, pasuk, "Observe the month of the spring."
שמרו שיבוא בחידושו, Shamru sheyavo bechidisho,
make sure that ניסן Nissan comes during its right time and during
the time of the spring. So of course they can add the
month, and that's their biblical role, and then of course the שמיטה
Shemita will be another month and it'll be פטור pattur from מעשרות,
Maasrot, but it has nothing to do with them directly making, you
know,
fields הפקר hefker and the consequence of that הפקר hefker being an
exemption from מעשרות. Maasrot. Okay, והיידא אמר דא, Vehaida amar da, okay,
that's an interesting like ירושלמי Yerushalmi thing, you know, והיכן אומר זה
Vehechan omer zeh is like what that phrase means. You know, where
is this type of a thing said? That you can, that their
act of making something הפקר hefker actually works?
So, hold on, let me just take a look one just one
second.
Right.
Yeah. Okay. So והיידא אמר דא, Vehaida amar da, where is this
said? גדי שלא לוקט תחתיו כל הנוגע בארץ הרי הן של עניים.
Gadi shelo lukat tachtav kol hanogea ba'aretz harei hen shel aniyim. So
let's say what you did is, you know, when you are like
the Book of Ruth, when you're gathering in your grain, then the
poor people are able to come and collect anything you drop. But
before letting them collect what you drop, you piled up your big
pile of grain in a certain space and you never first of
all made sure that that space underneath was cleared from the dropped
grain that the עניים aniyim could get. So what's the הלכה? halacha?
So the הלכה halacha is we say the whole bottom layer of
grain, anything that, any grain that's immediately touching the ground has a
status of לקט leket and the עניים aniyim can take it, under,
you know, on the bottom of your pile. Now if it has
a לקט, leket, what's the הלכה halacha of לקט? leket? Anything that
the עניים aniyim pick up, and that's מתנות עניים matnot aniyim or
whatever, is הפקר hefker and you don't give מעשרות. Maasrot. So you
see this is rabbinic. Biblically it's not all לקט. leket. Rabbinically we
made everything that touches the ground לקט, leket, with the consequences that
you won't take מעשרות. Maasrot. Okay, הרי זה של עניים. Harei zeh
shel aniyim. ואמר רבי אמי Ve'amar Rabbi Ami בשם רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, beshem Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, שדה שמאי היא זו. Sedei Shammai
hi zu. That actual הלכה halacha is only according to בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. How do you know that? דאי כבית הלל, De'i keveit
Hillel, work going like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, עניים אוכלין ומעשרין. Aniyim
ochlin ume'asrin. The עניים aniyim would have to take מעשרות. Maasrot. Why?
Because there's a famous debate of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, which is הפקר לעניים הפקר hefker la'aniyim hefker or
not? Can I make something הפקר hefker not to everybody but only
to a subset of people? הפקר Hefker might mean I remove my
ownership. If I remove my ownership, it's free for anyone. Can I
basically say no, if an עני ani takes it, then I've removed
my ownership, you know, it's הפקר hefker for the עניים aniyim not
for an עשיר. ashir. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it works
and בית הלל Beit Hillel says it does not work. So they're
saying according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, it doesn't have a status
of הפקר. hefker. So according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, maybe the
עניים aniyim can take it, but it never had a status of
הפקר hefker and therefore you'd have to take
מעשר. maaser. ואמר ליה רבי יוסי, Ve'amar lei Rabbi Yosei, ורבי יוסי
veRabbi Yosei says, no. שמענו שפטור מן המעשר דברי הכל משום קנסא.
Shamanu shepatur min hama'aser divrei hakol mishum kensa. No, actually everybody agrees,
even בית הלל, Beit Hillel, that this is not you making it
הפקר. hefker. You, you might not be able to make something הפקר
hefker only to the עניים. aniyim. That's a debate of בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, בית הלל. Beit Hillel. This is a rabbinic קנס kens
and again, הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker Beit Din hefker. And therefore
because it's a rabbinic קנס kens and making it הפקר, hefker, then
it's completely הפקר hefker although it's still true only the עניים aniyim
can get it, but it has the full status of הפקר hefker
and therefore even בית הלל Beit Hillel would agree that it's פטור
מן המעשר. patur min hama'aser. So this is our proof that once
בית דין Beit Din flexes their muscles and says הפקר בית דין
הפקר, hefker Beit Din hefker, it actually gets to the status of
being פטור מן המעשר. patur min hama'aser. Now I want to say
that, you know, again, what is the חידוש? chiddush? I mean if
it's הפקר hefker it's הפקר. hefker. Is the חידוש chiddush might be
that what does it mean הפקר בית דין הפקר? hefker Beit Din
hefker? You could conceptualize it the following way. You could say if
I go ahead and I take, if we made, בית דין Beit
Din made Michael's גמרא Gemara הפקר hefker there and I go ahead
and I take it, until I take it, it belongs to Michael.
But בית דין Beit Din has announced anybody who wants to grab
Michael's גמרא Gemara you're entitled to it. Okay, but he still owns
it until somebody grabs it. So then it was never really הפקר.
hefker. So then it would be חייב chayav in מעשר, ma'aser, right?
It went from being Michael's to being mine. So the חידוש chiddush
of being פטור ממעשר patur mi'ma'aser means that even before anybody has
taken it, we have removed this property from Michael's ownership and sort
of made it absolutely ownerless. And that's the חידוש chiddush that therefore
we would say it is even פטור patur from מעשר ma'aser because
it was a moment a period of being ownerless. All right, so
now let's go on, next משנה. mishnah. So that was about the
consequence of the כלאיים kilayim and, you know, and בית דין beis
din having to fine people
and make their property ownerless because people were abusing the system. And
now we go to the next משנה. mishnah. So we're moving on
from ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar to the fifteenth of אדר.
Adar.
Yeah, so in antiquity is there a
מסורת masoret from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
that the משניות mishnayot were actually not called משניות mishnayot or were
called הלכות? halachot? Oh, I don't know why it's הלכה, halachah, I
don't know where that nomenclature came from. I think that it's I'm
you know I think it's very post the גמרא Gemara itself. It's
late. It's late and it's a way of referring to ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
right? We also refer to the different תוספתא Tosefta as הלכה, halachah,
so as a way of dividing, so you know, it's תוספתא פרק
ג הלכה ב. Tosefta Perek Gimmel Halachah Bet. I don't know, I
don't know where it developed. Okay, בחמישה עשר בו, be-chamishah asar bo,
on the fifteenth of אדר, Adar, שולחנות היו יושבין במדינה, shulchanot hayu
yoshvin ba-medinah, the money changers would sit in the מדינה, medinah, there's
a question what מדינה medinah means, ירושלים, Yerushalayim, did it mean in
the major metropolis in, you know, metropolises? So they would, but anyway,
money changers would be around so you could go and change your
money in order to get your מחצית השקל. machtzis ha-shekel. בכ"ה, be-chof-hei,
on the twenty-fifth, right, ניסן Nisan is just around the corner, יושבין
במקדש, yoshvin ba-mikdash, they would be in the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash.
Again, it's a little bit funny, you would, you know, because you'd
think that people haven't given, why make them less accessible rather than,
you know, because of being in the מקדש, mikdash, it's in fewer
places. But anyway, so I don't really understand that fully, but anyway,
the money is getting closer to being brought to the מקדש, mikdash,
maybe you know your opportunities, you know, it's like if you do
it if you do it in advance you can register online, but
if you come late you have to actually go in person to
buy your tickets. So anyway, somehow somehow as it was getting later,
you know, all the money was finding its way to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and the money changers, maybe they were all still in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Yeah, but they wanted to be in on time, you know, and
then you want to make sure so you go there, make it
as close to the source. Exactly, exactly, once it's that late if
you've got to get it in in time you've got to bring
it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. משיושבו במקדש, misheyashvu ba-mikdash, התחילו למשכן. hitchilu le-mashken.
Now, from the time they sat in the מקדש, mikdash, anybody who
did not pay, they would they would start seizing their property. What's
the word? למשכן? le-mashken? Take as collateral? But basically a lien. Yeah,
I mean I'm trying to find a verb for that. Anyway, but
בית דין beis din would basically seize your property and hold it
as collateral until you paid up. They really wanted to ensure one
hundred percent participation. את מי ממשכנין, et mi memashkenin, who would they
do this for, seize their property to ensure they paid? לויים וישראלים,
leviyim ve-yisre'elim, גרים ועבדים משוחררים, gerim va-avadim meshuchrarim, לויים Leviyim and ישראלים,
Yisre'elim, converts and freed slaves, any basically male adult with the exceptions
of כהנים kohanim which we'll get to, אבל לא נשים, aval lo
nashim, not women because this is patterned after the מחצית השקל machtzis
ha-shekel in the תורה Torah which is men, ועבדים ve-avadim or slaves
which we normally put in the same category, וקטנים ve-katanim and minors.
Now, the interesting question is what defines minor? According to some גרסאות
girsa'ot in the גמרא Gemara we're about to read, minor's anybody under
twenty, based again on the פסוקים pesukim where it's מעשרים שנה ומעלה.
me-esrim shanah va-ma'alah. וכל קטן שהתחיל אביו לשקול על ידו, ve-chol katan
she-hitchil aviv lishkol al yado, any minor that the father began to
actually contribute for his sake, so already there was this idea of,
you know, giving for your for the minor children or minor boys
for the תמיד, Tamid, yes, just שוב shuv right the מחצית השקל,
machtzis ha-shekel, שוב אינו פוסק. shuv eino posek. Once you begin, you
can't stop giving. Okay, that sort of evokes the idea of once
you start doing something, you know, three times then you have to,
you're stuck with it. Anyway, but this is specifically in this context.
אין ממשכנין את הכהנים. ein memashkenin et ha-kohanim. Now why do you
not take the collateral from the כהנים? kohanim? So the first explanation
is מפני דרכי שלום, mipnei darchei shalom, for the ways of peace.
You know, they basically feel, hey, we're working in the בית המקדש
Beis Ha-Mikdash and now you're seizing our property for the stuff of
the בית המקדש? Beis Ha-Mikdash? Anyway, you don't want to get them
angry at you. So you know, they basically are still חייב chayav
but you don't use as much muscle to get the money from
them. אמר רבי יהודה העיד בן בוכרי ביבנה. amar Rabi Yehuda he'id
ben Buchri be-Yavneh. בן בוכרי Ben Buchri gave testimony in יבנה, Yavneh,
because in יבנה Yavneh right that was the first beginning of sort
of systematizing תורה שבעל פה Torah Shebe'al Peh after the חורבן הבית.
churban ha-bayis. They set up shop in יבנה, Yavneh, they got everybody
who had memories to testify about past practices. So he gave the
following testimony in יבנה. Yavneh. כל כהן ששוקל אינו חוטא. kol kohen
she-shokel eino chotei. Any כהן kohen that would give a שקל shekel
would not be sinning. Well okay, of course aren't you supposed to
give the שקל? shekel? But we're going to see in a minute
that the כהנים kohanim made an argument why they're not allowed to
give their שקל. shekel. Because if they give their שקל, shekel, they
have a part of קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibbur, and then the הלכה
halachah is that a מנחה minchah of a כהן kohen has to
be fully burned. So they'll say every מנחה, minchah, we can't have
כהן kohen ownership because then we'll have to burn every מנחה. minchah.
So they made a very a very... convenient argument to explain why
they not only were exempt but maybe shouldn't be giving a שקל.
shekel. So he said, if you want to give a שקל, shekel,
it's not a problem. So אמר לו Amar lo Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai who was the head of Yavneh at
this time, לא כי, lo ki, no, that's not the story. אלא
כל כהן שאינו שוקל חוטא, Ella kol kohen she'eino shokel chote, if
you don't give your שקל shekel you're sinning, meaning it's not that
it's okay to give a שקל, shekel, it's that you have to
give a שקל shekel and if not you're sinning. אלא שהכהנים דורשים
מקרא זה לעצמן, Ella shehakohanim dorshim mikra zeh le'atzman, but the כהנים
kohanim interpret the following פסוק pasuk to serve their own interest. And
how do they read that פסוק? pasuk? וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה
לא תאכל. Vechol minchat kohen kalil tihyeh lo te'achel. Any מנחה mincha
of a כהן kohen shall be totally burnt, cannot be eaten. So
they'll make the following argument: הואיל ועומר ושתי הלחם ולחם הפנים, Ho'il
ve'omer u'shtei halechem velechem hapanim, those are the מנחות minchot that are
communal where the money is going—the עומר, omer, the שתי הלחם, shtei
halechem, and לחם הפנים lechem hapanim every שבת, Shabbat, the עומר omer
and שתי הלחם shtei halechem is פסח Pesach and שבועות—שלנו הן, if
we would give our money to the communal sacrifices, those would partly
be ours. היך נאכלים, Heich ne'echalim, then they wouldn't be able to
be eaten. So in for the sake of the ציבור tzibur and
their interest, we will refuse to give our שקל, shekel, we have
to refuse to give our שקל. shekel. So it's fascinating, I have
to tell you though, psychologically it's a fascinating thing because a rabbi
who works for a שול, shul, or sort of like, "Well, I
don't have to give towards the appeal, right? I'm already working for
the שול, shul, I'm already giving all of my time." So it's
the same type of psychology, "Oh, I work for the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, I now have to donate for the קרבנות?" korbanot? So
they found a way to get themselves off. That's another way to
think about it. אין ממשכנין את הקטנים. Ein memashknin et haktanim. Let's
look at the גמרא. Gemara. You don't seize property for the קטנים.
ktanim. הא דתבועה תובעין, Ha ditvu'ah tvin, but you still ask for
them to give. So that's interesting, why would you ask for the
קטנים ktanim to give if they're not yet obligated? They could inherit
property anyway. הדא דתימר, Hada deteimar, this is only true, בהא עסקינן
beha askinan בשתי שערות. bishtei se'arot. He has two pubic hairs, which
presumably means he's bar mitzvahed, so he's not a קטן katan for
other purposes, so you would therefore still ask him to contribute. But
you don't demand it. אבל אם לא הביא שתי שערות לא בדבר.
Aval im lo heivi shtei se'arot lo bidavar. Less than two pubic
hairs, not. ולמשכן אין ממשכנין, Ulemashken ein memashknin, but you wouldn't actually
seize his property. Now there's a question how you read this, אף
על פי שהביא שתי שערות, af al pi sheheivi shtei se'arot, until,
even when he has two pubic hairs, and some have the גרסא
girsa עד שיהא בן עשרים. ad sheyehei ben esrim. That's in our
גרסא, girsa, but some have the גרסא, girsa, not the one printed
here, until he's twenty, which again is fascinating with what הלכה halacha
where twenty years matters, following the pattern of the פסוקים pesukim and
not the normal status of bar mitzvah. By the way, he's obligated
once he's thirteen, once he's bar mitzvahed, once he's an adult in
other הלכות, halachot, but you don't actually demand it and seize his
property until he's twenty. That's if you have that גרסא. girsa. If
you don't have that גרסא, girsa, you could argue that it means
two pubic hairs but he hasn't hit thirteen yet, although then why
the two hairs would matter is not clear. קיימי מתניתין Kaimei matnitin
אין ממשכנין את הכהנים מפני דרכי הכבוד. ein memashknin et hakohanim mipnei
darchei hakavod. So a way to read our משנה, Mishna, קיימי Kaimei
is a word that just sort of means like here's a way
of reading it or of establishing it. לשון נכון. Lashon nachon. Right,
נכון, nachon, like to frame it, so this is the way to
read our משנה Mishna that it's not what does it—דרכי שלום? darchei
shalom? דרכי שלום Darchei shalom here means to show respect to the
כהנים. kohanim. You want to keep them in their important status. The
whole thing here is for respect for the קרבנות korbanot and centrality
of the קרבנות, korbanot, you don't want it to start looking bad
that the כהנים kohanim are the ones that are being, their property
is being seized by בית דין. Beit Din. So you want to
hold them in a position of respect. Let's just finish the end
of the הלכה. halacha. אמר רבי יהודה העיד, Amar Rabbi Yehuda he'id,
so this convenient פסוק pasuk that they interpreted for their own interest.
אמר רבי ברכיה, Amar Rabbi Berechiah, היינו דרבי יוחנן בן זכאי, hainu
deRabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, the reason that רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai is clear that the כהנים kohanim give is זה
יתנו zeh yitnu from the פסוקים pesukim by the שקל. shekel. This
is what they should give. So זה zeh in גמטריא gematria is
12. י"ב שבטים יתנו, yud-bet shevatim yitnu, twelve tribes give. Of course,
if you know in the תורה, Torah, sometimes you can get twelve
without the כהנים kohanim and לויים, Leviyim, else it would have excluded
the לויים, Leviyim, not the כהנים. kohanim. Okay. רבי אבין בשם רב
המנונא, Rabbi Avin beshem Rav Hamnuna, כן משיבין חכמים לרבי יהודה. ken
meshivin chachamim leRabbi Yehuda. This is what the חכמים chachamim respond to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, in the משנה, Mishna, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
who said that the כהנים kohanim didn't give. So חטאת יחיד מתה,
chatat yachid meta, here's the answer to your point that a communal
sacrifice, we would have a part of it and it would be
a כהן. kohen. Basically, there's a big difference between a communal sacrifice
and a private sacrifice. And here's how they prove it. חטאת יחיד
מתה, Chatat yachid meta, if you have an individual חטאת chatat that
let's say something happens to it, the owner dies or whatever, the
חטאת chatat has to be put to death, has to let die.
אין חטאת ציבור מתה, Ein chatat tzibur meta, but you wouldn't say
it by a communal חטאת. chatat. So obviously, once something is communal,
communal is not a lot of individuals. Communal is a completely different
corporate entity. So even if the כהנים kohanim give to a communal
מנחה, mincha, it's not going to make it a כהן's kohen מנחה.
mincha. Fully, מנחת יחיד קרבה כליל, Minchas yachid kareva kalil, a private
כהן's Kohen מנחה Mincha would be burnt up fully, ואין מנחת ציבור
קרבה כליל, ve'ein Minchas Tzibur kareva kalil, it wouldn't be true about
a communal that you still are part of the community and you
still have to give. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara just makes
the point, the קשיא, kasha, we've got a problem. משיבין לאדם דבר
שאינו מודה בו? Meshivin l'adam davar she'eino modeh bo? How can you
challenge רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda on a point that he doesn't concede?
What point does he not concede? דתנן, Detnan, שאין חטאת ציבור מתה,
she'ein chatas tzibur mesa, רבי יהודה אומר תמות. Rebbi Yehuda omer tamus.
The whole example you gave of the difference between a private חטאת
chatas and a communal one, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda doesn't hold of.
רבי יהודה holds that actually a communal חטאת chatas also is allowed
to die. So how can you say look, a proof to you,
ציבור's tzibur different than יחיד yachid from the case of a חטאת?
chatas? He doesn't even concede the case of a חטאת. chatas. והוא
מותיב להן, V'hu mosiv lan, no, and he would respond that no,
even with that, זו לא נדבת יחיד היא ואינן משיבין לה ואינון
משיבין ליה, zo lo nidvas yachid hi v'einan masivin lah v'inan matvin
leh, they would still say that this is still a private thing,
a private contribution, and therefore you can challenge based on the difference
between a private and a public, even if he doesn't concede the
point about the חטאת. chatas. Now, כיון שנמסר לציבור כמי שהוא נדבת
ציבור, Keivan shenimsar latzibur k'mi shehu nidvas tzibur, once it is given,
and this is the reason behind it, once you make a contribution
even as a יחיד, yachid, then it's given and it's given over
to the ציבור, tzibur, then it becomes communal. It's no longer your
private, I own point two percent of that קרבן. korban. Now it
becomes communal and therefore basically what it's saying is, you know what,
he might not concede the case of חטאת, chatas, but he should
be able to admit to this just based on sort of like
self-evident, you know, that there's a fundamental difference between a private contribution
and something that becomes part of a public and communal fund. Okay,
now we'll just end this. כתיב, Ksiv, the פסוק pasuk says, כל
העובר על הפקודים, Kol ha'over al hapikudim, anybody that passes over the
counting. רבי יהודה ורבי נחמיה, Rebbi Yehuda v'Rebbi Nechemia, חד אמר, Chad
omer, כל דעבר בימא, kol d'avar b'yama, it's like this phrase כל
העובר, kol ha'over, so it means anybody that passed through the ים
סוף. Yam Suf. Okay, I don't know how you get that from
פקודים, pikudim, פקוד ימא pikud-yama or some phrase. Anyway, anybody that passed
through the
ים סוף Yam Suf has to give. יתן. Yitein. וחנא אמר, V'chana
omer, and חנא Chana is אחר Acheir says, the other one says,
כל דעבר על פקודיא יתן. kol d'avar al pikudaya yitein. No, from
here on in, who gives? Only people that were part of אלה
הפקודים. eileh hapikudim. And as we know, the כהנים kohanim, had a
separate count. Actually, again, it wasn't just the כהנים, kohanim it was
actually also the לויים. Levi'im. So again, this is a little strange,
that argument. But okay. מאן דאמר, Man d'amar, כל דעבר בימא יתן,
kol d'avar b'yama yitein, מסייע misayeia לרבי יוחנן בן זכאי, l'Rebbi Yochanan
ben Zakkai, because that means everybody has to give, so that supports
the position of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. Rebbi Yochanan ben Zakkai. ומאן
דאמר, U'man d'amar, כל דעבר על פקודיא יתן, kol d'avar al pikudaya
yitein, and the one that says only those that were part of
the normal counting give, מסייע misayeia לבן בוכרי, l'Ben Buchri, that supports
בן בוכרי Ben Buchri who says that the
כהנים fundamentally do not have to give. That's a really interesting מחלוקת.
Machlokes. Yeah.